<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-21T14:14:09+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Hasan Faisal</title><subtitle>Feel free to reach out!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">You can learn anything, given enough time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You can learn anything, given enough time" /><published>2025-01-20T00:32:58+05:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T00:32:58+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the continuation to my LinkedIn <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/hasanfaesal_you-can-learn-anything-given-enough-time-activity-7276710765573607424-cFrE?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">post</a></p>

<p>As humans we must always adhere to some goals, seeking knowledge and truth is one of them. Hence, one must keep on learning till death. “Lifelong student” is a term that describes this the best.</p>

<p>However, I was a person who never liked studying till now. I can say that I’ve wasted my life upto getting admission in University.</p>

<p>Understanding how the system works took me an awful lot of a semester, and why it is like that maybe another 4 months. I tried changing it, didn’t work out. I thought to myself, what can I do now?</p>

<h1 id="first-thing-to-learn-in-this-age">First thing to learn in this age</h1>
<p>Over the course of 4 months, I learnt a basic but important thing : “How to use the Internet”. I didn’t knew that the Internet was a really interesting place and trust me alot of people still don’t know it. Perhaps, LLMs are changing this from a different perspective. Everything is available on the Internet, mostly for free so why are you holding back?</p>

<h1 id="the-start-of-my-journey---tutorial-hell">The start of my journey - tutorial hell?</h1>
<p>In my 2nd semester, I asked advice from a senior regarding what to do? Having so much time, I wanted to invest in myself. He told me to start learning Data Structures and Algorithms. I followed his advice and covered the majority of the course in 2.5 months. I continued to study Machine Learning in my summer vacations.</p>

<h1 id="reviewing-back-on-time">Reviewing back on time</h1>

<p>I scrolled through my gallery to view old photos and I stumbled upon this one.</p>

<p>//insert image</p>

<p>One thing went through my mind, I’m better than I was 1 year ago. Throughout this year, I had my ups and downs thinking that will I ever be a professional? The answer is quite certain, your confidence increases as your learning does.</p>

<h1 id="learn-anything">Learn Anything</h1>
<p>The conclusion I draw is one can learn anything, given enough time and effort. I had never studied Computer Science before in my life but alot has changed within the time span of a year. A year earlier, I could never have imagined myself learning these disciplines and doing these <a href="https://github.com/hasanfaesal">projects</a> and yet here I am.
This is best described in Sal Khan’s TED <a href="https://youtu.be/-MTRxRO5SRA?si=DZHaysO6NFOglQ1D">talk</a></p>

<p>I have more to do.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the continuation to my LinkedIn post]]></summary></entry></feed>