<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-20T22:41:52+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Hasan Faisal</title><subtitle>an AI Student</subtitle><entry><title type="html">You can teach anything, given enough devotion?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/19/teach-anything.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You can teach anything, given enough devotion?" /><published>2025-03-19T00:32:58+05:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T00:32:58+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/19/teach-anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/19/teach-anything.html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="disclaimer"><strong><em>Disclaimer:</em></strong></h4>
<p><strong><em>These are my personal views based on my experiences. I’m not a prodigy who knows everything—I’m just someone trying to make the best use of my time. I highly respect all of my teachers.</em></strong></p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Since the start of my bachelor’s degree, <em>I’ve lost interest in multiple courses, resulting in low attendance.</em> Each day begins by logging into the CMS to ensure my attendance will meet the minimum requirement of 75%.</p>

<p>Repeatedly, I’ve attempted to attend classes but usually end up convincing myself that doing something else is more productive. Here are two examples from my 4th semester:</p>

<h4 id="entrepreneurship">Entrepreneurship</h4>

<p>Our professor once mentioned that we should be glad our class is two hours instead of three. Surprised, I wondered how I’d even spend those two hours and responded that 1.5 hours would be optimal. Immediately, I was met with the counter-question: <em>“What is your experience in education?”</em></p>

<p>Turns out I had <strong>‘offended’</strong> my professor.</p>

<p>Soon after, bored by the decade-old slides, I opened <em>YouTube</em> to watch some tech content. Meanwhile, my classmate was performing market analysis on his laptop. We both were <em>instructed to turn off our devices</em> and pay attention to the lecture. Fair enough.</p>

<h4 id="data-communication-and-networking">Data Communication and Networking</h4>

<p>The instructor was covering basics such as data representation (text, numbers, audio, images, videos, etc.). Having already worked extensively with tensors and multimodal data, I wasn’t particularly engaged.</p>

<p>Curious about what the course offered, I turned to <em>Perplexity</em> on my phone, only to be told by the instructor to put away my device. When I explained I was searching for questions related to the course, she insisted that I should have asked her instead.</p>

<p>I informed her that I had numerous questions—some meaningful, others unrelated or complex but I wasn’t excused. I asked a few questions I’d already searched for online and received vague responses — essentially <strong>gibberish</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Many Pakistani professors tend not to admit when they don’t know the answer</strong>. They’d rather make something up on the spot. I’ve taken enough <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenCourseWare">OCW</a> courses to appreciate professors who respond with <em>“I’ll look into that and get back to you,”</em> acknowledging when they’re unsure or need more clarity.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="a-question-for-instructors">A Question for Instructors</h2>

<p>Have you ever wondered why students don’t pay attention in class? They’re either scrolling through reels, browsing the web, chatting, or even sleeping.</p>

<p>I’ll answer this question for you because I’ve personally done all of the above, including frequently napping during lectures.</p>

<p>Here are <em>some</em> reasons behind such behavior:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Lack of interaction</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Irrelevant subjects</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Restrictions on device usage</strong></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="1-lack-of-interaction">1. Lack of interaction</h3>

<p>I was listening to a podcast featuring <a href="http://yann.lecun.com/">Yann LeCun</a>, who emphasized that the primary difference between recorded and live lectures is <strong>interaction</strong>.</p>

<p>Many of our professors simply read from slides without actively engaging students or encouraging questions. This one-way communication makes it challenging for students to remain attentive or actively participate.</p>

<p>Pausing briefly between topics to ask thought-provoking questions can significantly boost engagement. If students lack motivation to participate, incorporating incentives such as bonus marks for correct answers can help.</p>

<h3 id="2-irrelevant-subjects">2. Irrelevant subjects</h3>

<p>Here’s our <a href="https://archive.bahria.edu.pk/index.php/academics/under-graduate-programs/bsai/">roadmap</a> for the Bachelor of Science in Artificial Intelligence program. Courtesy of the Higher Education Commission (HEC) Pakistan, some courses simply don’t align with the degree.</p>

<p>For instance, teaching university-level students “Functional English” after they’ve spent 12 years mastering language fundamentals is unnecessary. Such courses consume valuable time and resources without adding meaningful value.</p>

<p>These are listed as <strong>General Education Courses</strong>, comprising <strong>30 out of 133 total credit hours</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="3-restrictions-on-device-usage">3. Restrictions on device usage</h3>

<p>We encounter different types of teachers each with unique teaching styles, temperaments and rules. Similarly, we must recognize that students have varying learning styles and needs.</p>

<p>Some students hesitate to ask questions, others struggle with the pace of the course and some have endless queries or curiosity etc.</p>

<p>Allowing laptop usage during lectures can address many of these issues. In fact, most reputable online courses, such as <a href="https://cs50.harvard.edu/x/2025/">Harvard’s CS50x</a> arguably the best <strong>Introduction to Computer Science</strong> course globally actively encourages device usage. Students engage by coding, note-taking, reviewing slides, and interacting meaningfully in class.</p>

<p><em>So why do our professors enforce strict rules against using laptops in class?</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: These are my personal views based on my experiences. I’m not a prodigy who knows everything—I’m just someone trying to make the best use of my time. I highly respect all of my teachers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You can learn anything, given enough time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You can learn anything, given enough time" /><published>2025-01-20T00:32:58+05:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T00:32:58+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/20/learn-anything.html"><![CDATA[<p>**INCOMPLETE but just pushed the changes</p>

<p>This is the continuation to my LinkedIn <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/hasanfaesal_you-can-learn-anything-given-enough-time-activity-7276710765573607424-cFrE?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">post</a></p>

<p>As humans we must always adhere to some goals, seeking knowledge and truth is one of them. Hence, one must keep on learning till death. “Lifelong student” is a term that describes this best.</p>

<p>However, I was a person who never liked studying. I can say that I’ve wasted my life upto getting admission in University.</p>

<p>Understanding how the education system works took me my first semester and why it is like that and doesn’t change maybe another 4 months. I tried changing it, didn’t work out. I thought to myself, what can I do now?</p>

<h1 id="first-thing-to-learn-in-this-age">First thing to learn in this age</h1>
<p>Over the course of 4 months, I learnt a basic but important thing : “How to use the Internet”. I didn’t knew that the Internet had all of the answers, you just have to find them and trust me alot of people still don’t know it. 
Perhaps, LLMs are changing this? Perplexity is a great answer engine which makes this easier.
Everything is available on the Internet, mostly for free so why was I holding back?</p>

<p>To this day, still I’m discovering the best practices of using the Internet. <a href="https://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">How to Ask Questions The Smart Way</a> by Eric Steven Raymond is an article I’ve read recently on how to ask questions the correct way.</p>

<h1 id="the-start-of-my-journey">The start of my journey</h1>
<!-- Resize the image using inline HTML -->
<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/learn-anything2.jpg" alt="1st week of university - a picture of lecture hall" width="50%" />
  <figcaption>1st week of university (September 20, 2023)</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In my 2nd semester, I asked for advice from a senior regarding what to do in my free time? I wanted to invest in myself having enough time. He told me to start learning Data Structures and Algorithms and I followed his advice and covered the majority of the course in 2.5 months. I continued to study Machine Learning in my summer vacations.</p>

<h1 id="reviewing-back-on-time">Reviewing back on time</h1>
<p>I scrolled through my gallery to view old photos and I stumbled upon this one.</p>

<!-- Resize the image using inline HTML -->
<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/learn-anything1.jpg" alt="Roadmap up to 8 months" width="50%" />
  <figcaption>A roadmap I created in library</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>One thing went through my mind, I’m better than I was 1 year ago. Throughout this year, I had been continuously doubting myself that whether I’ll be capable enough or not. The answer is quite certain, your confidence increases as your learning does. You gain certainity in your abilities.</p>

<h1 id="never-finished">Never finished</h1>
<p>I believe I should’ve done more in this time span. I could’ve done more, however I’ll implement the practices I’ve learnt further in my journey. 
“The best way to learn is by doing”</p>

<h1 id="learn-anything">Learn Anything</h1>
<p>The conclusion I draw is one can learn anything, given enough time and effort. I had never studied Computer Science before in my life but alot has changed within the time span of a year. A year earlier, I could never have imagined myself learning these disciplines and doing these <a href="https://github.com/hasanfaesal">projects</a> and yet here I am.
This is best described in Sal Khan’s TED <a href="https://youtu.be/-MTRxRO5SRA?si=DZHaysO6NFOglQ1D">talk</a></p>

<p>I have more to do.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[**INCOMPLETE but just pushed the changes]]></summary></entry></feed>